Hey, hey. What's up, my friend? So, in
today's video, I want to share with you
why most traders fail with technical
analysis. If you were to ask me to put a
number, a percentage to it, I would say
90 95% of traders just lose money using
technical analysis. And why is that? Let
me explain. So, here's the thing, right?
Technical analysis, it comprises of many
different tools. So, if I were to
illustrate, right, imagine this entire
circle. It
comprises like the umbrella, right?
Technical analysis is like the umbrella.
And beneath this umbrella, there's a lot
of different tools, right? You have
things like RSI, you have support
resistance, you have price action, you
have chart patterns, you have
candlestick patterns, you have uh what a
stochastic, you have pivot points, etc.
So there's so many different tools under
this umbrella called technical
analysis. And here's the thing, right?
Why do some traders find success with
this approach while the majority fail?
And that's the
question. And a big reason is because
the tools that you're using, it does not
complement one another. Let me
explain. Imagine this, right? You're all
hyped up to showcase, right, a new car
that you have built to the world. You
spend your years building this supercar
of yours in your garage. And this car of
yours, it has three airons, right? Three
AC, two for you, one for your wife
because you need to show her who's boss.
It has two gearboxes for extra speed and
five wheels, right? Because you like odd
numbers. But guess what?
You didn't build a
car but a huge useless paper
weight. And the point I'm trying to make
over here is that technical analysis
right is like this if the tools that
you're using does not complement one
another. Yeah, it's just going to be a
huge paper weight like the car. So now
the question is how should you then use
technical analysis such that it
complements one another. So this is
where you need to make sure technical
analysis tells you these four things.
Number one, it tells you what are the
conditions of your trading setup. When
do you enter a trade? When do you take
profit? And when do you cut loss. So let
me give you an example of
how all this comes together. So let's
say you have
a a pullback trading system, right?
You're identifying stocks that are in an
uptrend like this. You're waiting for a
pullback. You're buying on a pullback.
And let's say you wait for a bounce and
look to sell let's
say at resistance to capture a swing. So
how can you then use technical analysis
to bring out this trading idea to this
trading concept such that you can
actually use it to trade it in the live
market. So here's how. So you know the
idea the concept of behind this trading
system. So what I will do then is number
one ask yourself what are the conditions
of your trading setup? How can you use
technical analysis to define the
condition of the trading setup that you
want to trade? So in this case, what you
can do is that you can use a tool like
the moving average. For example, the
price has to be above the 200 day moving
average. So this is where the moving
average comes into play. It has a
purpose to help you define the trend
where the price must be above the 200
day moving
average. Next one, when do you enter? So
you're looking to buy on a pullback. So
what technical analysis tools can you
use to help you define a pullback? There
there are many out there. So for example
in this case let's say we go with the
RSI okay the RSI value okay we are
looking to make sure that the RSI value
let's say is below 30 for example right
to define a pullback right and you enter
maybe let's say uh when the RSI is below
30 that's an example when do you take
profit or let's say you take profit at
resistance or before resistance yeah so
using the concept of a price action
support resistance and when do you cut
loss let's say if the price breaks
support you cut loss. So can you see how
we are now using all these different
technical analysis tools to bring to
life the trading concept the trading
strategy that you have in mind by
answering these four questions over here
and this is how you use technical
analysis to complement your trading. You
don't want just want to slap you know 10
moving averages on your chart because
it's not going to deliver any extra
value. is like having you three steering
wheels, two gearboxes doesn't make
sense. Yeah. So this is how right you
want to approach technical analysis and
how to make it complement one another.
And here are two pro tips that I have
for you when it comes to technical
analysis. So every tool, every
indicator, every line on your chart, it
must have a purpose. If not, remove it.
Trading is not about, it's not like a
beauty contest where you're trying to
make your charts as pretty as possible.
see who has the prettiest looking chart,
right? And then you win prize money.
Doesn't work that way. Okay? So, what
this does is that if you don't if you
don't do this, right, what you're going
to get is that you're going to get
conflicting signals, analysis,
paralysis, and distract you from the
things that matter, distract you away
from your own trading plan, right? You
get conflicting signals because let's
say you have multiple indicators on your
chart. One indicator say buy, the other
one say sell. Which one do you follow?
There you have it. Conflicting signals.
You get analysis paralysis where you
have so many things on the chart. You
analyze, analyze, analyze and do you
feel confused and frustrated? I know
what should I do now? Close your monitor
and you know take a break. Right? That's
the probably the thing you need to do or
even worse distract you from your
trading plan. You really don't have a
plan but because you have so many things
on your chart it distract you from the
things that matter which is your trading
plan. So this is why every tool on your
charts every line indicator must have a
purpose. If not just delete it. It's not
going to add you it's not going to you
know make you a more profitable trader
by having a ton of nonsense on it.
So now moving on right I also want to
talk about another reason why many
traders fail with technical analysis and
it's because they don't have an H in the
markets. Their trading system doesn't
have an H. What does that mean? So an H
right is something you do repeatedly
that yields a positive outcome and a H
can be quantified using this formula
over here. Let me explain. It's not
difficult. E right some people call it
expectancy. So if your E is positive it
means that you have a positive
expectancy. If it's negative then
negative expectancy. Your winning
percentage is just your winning rate.
How often you win. Average gain is that
what is the size of your average
winners. And this is just the opposite.
Your losing rate and size of your
average losers. So let me give you an
example so you can see how this works.
So imagine this. Imagine you toss a
coin. Every time it comes up head, you
win $2, right? And what are the odds of
it coming up heads? 30%, right? Ah, just
kidding. It's 50%, right? If you toss a
coin, you know that 50% of the time it's
going to come up hit. Likewise, if you
toss a coin, 50% of the time it's going
to come up
tail. So now with this numbers that you
have, you can actually plug in into this
formula I shared earlier. So this will
be 50%, average gain is $2, 50% is your
losing rate, and your average loss is a
dollar. And there you have it. So your E
is 0.5. What does the E means? Simply
put, right, it means that on average,
whenever you toss a coin, on average,
you can expect to make about 50 cents,
50 p wherever you are in the world,
right? Singapore, we call it cents, 50
cents per coin toss. And if you toss the
coin a 100 times, you can expect to make
around $50, right, at the end of the 100
tosses of the coin. Okay, so this is how
you actually use the E expectancy. But
the key thing over here is that you want
to make sure that your E, your
expectancy is positive. If it's
negative, it means that you don't have
an edge in the markets and you pretty
much, you know, need to refine it or
find something else altogether. And this
brings me to the next question. How do
you find an edge in the markets? You
guys are probably thinking, but Rain,
you know, how do I find an edge in the
market? It's not that easy, man. You
know, if it's so easy, right? All of us
were printing money, right? Like a
casino, right? So, there are a few
approaches to it. Number one, you got to
back test your trading system, your
strategy based on proven concepts. And
this is actually the approach I I go
with that I myself personally like to
use, right? Because it's more efficient.
You can get results much faster. So you
going to back test a trading system and
idea and see how he has performed over
the last 5 years, 10 years, 20 years,
etc. For those of you who are more of a
price action trader, discretionary
trader, you probably want to forward
test it. If back testing is too is not
too practical for you, you want to
forward test it in the live markets and
see how it performs. And even price
action traders, you are actually able to
do back testing as well. So for testing
is if you want to take things a step
further and see how it performs in the
live markets over the next one two 3
months. Yeah. And of course right this
takes a ton of work. In fact I think
this is the one of the hardest part
about trading finding an age in the
markets. And this is why if you want to
shortcut your learning curve you can go
down to my website over here
tradingwithra.com. Okay the link is over
here and download this guide for free.
This guide is called the essential guide
to systems trading where I'll share with
you how to
actually find trading strategies that
has an edge in the markets using this
proven formula of mine and I'll even
share with you a simple trading system
that has an edge in the market. So you
can use it as a framework to develop
your own trading systems if you wish to.
Yeah. But all in all, this guide I would
say is essential, right? If you want to
shortcut your learning curve and trade
with strategies that has an age in the
markets. Now moving
on. Another reason why many traders fail
is because system
hopping.
Okay, let me ask you right. Have you
ever come across learn a new trading
system? Could be from a website, a book,
blog, whatsoever. And you're excited
about Yeah. Right. A new trading
strategy, a new system. Hya. So at the
start, you have a few winners, right?
Three, four, five winning trades in a
row. And then slowly you face your first
loss, your second
loss, and before you know it, you're
down five losing trades in a
row. At this point, right, you start to
doubt yourself. You start to wonder to
yourself questions like, man, did the
trading system stop working? You know,
did the market conditions change? Did I
do something
wrong? And what do you do? Well, after
five losses in a row, you think that
man, this system is no longer working.
Maybe the market conditions have
changed. Let me find something else,
something better, faster,
cheaper. Just kidding. Right? In
Singapore, we're always looking for
something faster, better, cheaper. But,
you know, when in trading doesn't quite
work that way. So, you look for
something newer,
fresher, and then this process will just
rinse, repeat itself again, right? find
something new. Winners, losers, give up,
find something else again. But here's
the thing, right? If you look at this
results over here, this is a trading
system, right, that I teach in my book
called trading systems that work. And I
want to highlight to you something
important over here. If you look at
this, this system have has like five,
okay, if you just ignore this one over
here, like four losing months in a row.
meaning four to five months in a row
this system has lost money and it's not
the first time it's doing this if you
look at over here there's like three
losing months in a row we have a 18%
drop right in 1998 for this system over
here you have another four losing months
in a
row okay so what's the point I'm trying
to make the point I'm trying to make is
that every profitable trading system if
even if it has an age in the markets you
will face a series of losses you will
face draw down and if you were to quit
in the midst of a draw
down then what you're doing is that you
will not see the better days ahead. You
will not be able to reap rewards like
this. Right? If you look at this right
in 2006 right a draw down occurred which
is somewhere about here. Right? If you
give up and not able to write out the
draw down over here you miss out right
this exponential profits right in the
later years. And this will be the same
for every trading system. You're going
to face a draw down. If you hop from
system to system, there's no way there's
no way you can be a consistently
profitable
trader. All right? So, you have to
embrace the
losses. And by the way, if you want to
grab a copy of uh the book Trading
Systems that work, I'll put the link
below this video at the description. You
can see over here, we will pretty much
uh this book contains three different
trading systems for you to profit in
bull and bare markets even during a
recession, right? You can go down to the
link over here, trading systemsbook.com,
and grab a copy. And here's the thing,
right? It's risk- free, right? If within
180 days, you grab a copy of the book,
you don't like it, just email us and
we'll happily refund you in full, no
questions asked, right? So, this is kind
of risk-free for you, right? So, just
click this uh orange button, right? And
you can uh grab a copy of this book.
Now, moving on. The question is this,
right? How do you then avoid system
hopping? Few things you must be aware
of. Number one, you must have data on
your trading system like you know what
is the winning rate, what is the maximum
percentage draw down etc. So you have a
frame of reference to
know how the system perform is
performing now relative to the past
right? So let's say the historical draw
down is maximum draw down is 30 35%. So
right now if you're at 30 35% you want
to ask yourself right did something
change the market conditions change is
it supposed to be performing well in
this market condition or not? So this is
where the second question to ask
yourself is this right? Know when your
trading system underperform right? So if
you are you know like trading a stock
trading system a trend following stock
system where you are supposed to profit
in a bull market then guess what in a
bare market during a recession that
system is supposed to lose money and you
shouldn't freak out because that's the
nature of that system. No trading system
is going to profit in all market
conditions. It's important to know the
market conditions that your trading
system will perform well in and the
system will underperform in. So when a
trading system underperforms, right? You
you then know, right? Is it due to the
market conditions or something else
altogether? All
right. And here's a pro tip for you,
right? Understand that trading is all
about probabilities, not certainty. I
think I'm not sure who I heard that
from, right? But this quote really stick
with me. Trading is about probabilities,
never certainty. You can lose 10 trades
in a row and it's still within the
realm of possibility, right? Even though
it's a profitable trading system,
especially trading system that has a low
winning rate like, you know, trend
following 40 45%. It's common to see,
you know, 10 12 13 losses in a row. But
if you have the data to back up your
trading system, if you have a data and
you know that you have an age in the
markets, you got to power through this,
right? Instead of, you know, system
hopping from one system to another. So
with that said, right, let's do a quick
recap to what we've covered so far. The
three main reasons why traders lose with
technical analysis is number one, they
don't have a trading plan. Okay, their
tools are not even complimenting one
another usually at conflict. Number two,
they don't have an edge in the markets.
If you don't have an edge in the
markets, you won't have conviction in
your trading system. And if you don't
have conviction in your trading system,
it will lead you to system hop, right?
So all
these reasons, right, they're kind of
like intertwined and linked to one
another. Okay? And before I go, I
noticed myself keep saying the word
okay. Okay. So, okay, before I go, you
can go down to my website,
tradingfrainer.com, and grab a copy of
this guide, the essential guide to
systems trading, where I share with you
how to develop proven trading systems
that work, plus even give you a trading
system, right, as a framework that you
can use to profit from the market. So,
with that said, I wish you good luck,
good trading. I'll put the details, the
link in the description below. Go and
check it out and I will talk to you
soon.